Guide to the Catherine Roraback Collection of Ericka Huggins Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Catherine Roraback Collection of Ericka Huggins Papers
1961-2000
1969-1971
JWJ MSS 96
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.67
(10 boxes)
The Catherine Roraback Collection of Ericka Huggins papers consists of materials compiled by attorney Catherine Roraback during the New Haven trial of Black Panther Party leader Ericka Huggins. Included in the collection are Huggins' legal files, prison writings, clippings, correspondence and other documentation of the trial and Huggins' imprisonment.
Roraback, Catherine, 1920-2007
Huggins, Ericka
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 10 contains restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bolerium Books on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 2012.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Ericka Huggins Trial Proceedings (1961-2000). II. Correspondence (1969-1972). III. Ericka Huggins Personal Papers (1969-1975).
Catherine Roraback (1920-2007)
Catherine Roraback was a Connecticut civil rights attorney who served as lead defense counsel for Ericka Huggins during her trial for the kidnapping and murder of Alex Rackley. Roraback was born on September 17, 1920 in Brooklyn, New York City, New York. She graduated from Mount Holyoke College in 1941 and was the only woman to graduate from Yale University Law School in 1948. Upon graduation, Roraback took over her family's law practice in Canaan, Connecticut. From 1969 to 1971, Roraback defended Ericka Huggins, a leader in the New Haven chapter of the Black Panther Party who was charged with conspiracy in the murder of Alex Rackley, a member of the Black Panther Party. On May 25 1971, the trial ended in a hung jury and was declared a mistrial. After the trial, Roraback continued to practice law and participated in organizations such as the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, an organization she co-founded, and became president of the National Lawyers Guild. Roraback died on October 17, 2007 in Salisbury, Connecticut.
Ericka Huggins (1948-)
Ericka Jenkins Huggins was born in Washington D.C. on January 5, 1948. Huggins attended Lincoln University where she met her husband, John Huggins, and together they moved to California to join the Black Panther Party. John Huggins was murdered by members of the rival black nationalist US Organization on the University of California, Los Angeles campus in 1969. After his death, Huggins relocated to New Haven, Connecticut with their daughter Mai and became a leader in the New Haven chapter of the Black Panther Party. On May 22, 1969, Huggins, along with Black Panther Party co-founder Bobby Seale, faced charges that stemmed from the kidnapping and murder of Black Panther Party member Alex Rackley. The trial, which lasted from October 1970 to May 1971, ended in a mistrial and dismissal of all charges. Huggins was released on May 25, 1971. After the trial, Huggins remained in the Black Panther Party and became the director of the Oakland Community School in Oakland, California until 1981. She also became the first black woman and first woman to be appointed to the Alameda County Board of Education. Huggins also worked as a professor of sociology and African American studies in the Peralta Community College District.
Scope and Contents
Materials in the Catherine Roraback collection of Ericka Huggins papers document the activities of both Catherine Roraback and Ericka Huggins during the New Haven Black Panther trials. A majority of the collection contains Catherine Roraback's legal files related to Ericka Huggins's trial, including memoranda on prison conditions, statements, depositions, affidavits, and FBI reports. Materials belonging to Ericka Huggins includes poems, correspondence, and other writings created during her imprisonment. Communist reading material requested by Huggins such as The Selected Writings of Mao Tse-Tung (1968) are also included.
African American political activists; African Americans -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Black militant organizations -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Black power -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Lawyers -- United States; Political activists -- United States; Trials (Conspiracy) -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Trials (Kidnapping) -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Trials (Murder) -- Connecticut -- New Haven; New Haven (Conn.) -- Race relations; Lawyers -- United States -- 20th Century; Political activists -- United States -- 20th Century; Huggins, Ericka; Roraback, Catherine, 1920-2007; Black Panther Party
- Ericka Huggins Trial Proceedings, 1961-2000; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of Catherine Roraback's legal files documentating the trial of New Haven Black Panther Party leader Ericka Huggins. Trial statements made by members of the Black Panther Party include those from Ericka Huggins, George Sams, and Loretta Luckes. Copies of FBI files documenting the movements of the Black Panther party including a statement by former FBI director J. Edgar Hoover are contained within this series. The series also contains media covering the New Haven Black Panther Party Trial including press from the Panther Trial News, the Liberation News Service, and clippings from various news outlets such as The New Yorker, The New York Times, and The New Haven Register. A petition to free Ericka Huggins as well as memoranda and correspondence from lawyers and Yale Officials regarding the trial and Yale May Day protests are also included.
  - Access to clients, 1969; cuid0 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Affidavit: State of Connecticut Vs. Ericka Huggins, 1969; cuid1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autopsy report and examination of Alex Rackley's body, 1969–1970; cuid2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bail and appeal on bail law, Circa 1970; cuid3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bail fund, 1970–1971; cuid4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Black Against Black: The Agony of Panthermania" article by Gail Sheehy with criticisms by Harry S. Huggins., 1970–1971; cuid5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Black Panther Party depositions on Alex Rackley, 1970; cuid6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bobby Seale motions and memorandum, 1969–1971; cuid7 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Bobby Seale, 1969-; cuid8 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 128)
  - Capital punishment, 1961–1969; cuid9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Challenge to array memorandum of facts, law and statistical information, Circa 1968-1974; cuid10 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Clippings, Circa 1969-1973; cuid11 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 129-130)
  - Companion cases, pleadings, 1968–1969; cuid12 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Competency of witnesses, Circa 1969; cuid13 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Complaint to the U.S. District Court, Circa 1970-1971; cuid14 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Connecticut Correctional Commission: mail and reading policy in prison, 1969–1971; cuid15 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Conspiracy Law, 1969–1971; cuid16 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Court bills, 1969–1971; cuid17 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cumulative due process, Circa 1965-1971; cuid18 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Current legal research problems, 1970–1971; cuid19 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Current legal research problems, 1971; cuid20 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 131)
  - Death penalty, Circa 1968-1971; cuid21 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dismissal of material witnesses, Circa 1970; cuid22 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ericka Huggins's seized materials in May 22, 1969 search, cuid23 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - Ericka Huggins's trial notes, Circa 1969-1971; cuid24 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Evidence questions, 1964–1971; cuid25 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - False arrests, Circa 1962-1971; cuid26 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - FBI et al suit pleadings, 1971; cuid27 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - FBI memos, 1969–2000; cuid28 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - FBI personnel and materials, 1968–1971; cuid29 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - FBI personnel and materials, Circa 1968-1971; cuid30 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 132)
  - FBI wiretap and surveillance pleadings, and memoranda, Circa 1965-2000; cuid31 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - FBI wiretap and surveillance pleadings, and memoranda, Circa 1965-2000; cuid32 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 133)
  - Final argument notes, Circa 1970-1971; cuid33 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Frank Hawley case, 1970; cuid34 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 134)
  - George Sams legal documents and statements, 1969–1970; cuid35 (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
  - George Sams legal documents and statements, 1971; cuid36 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 135)
  - Grand jury proceedures and indictments, 1970–1971; cuid37 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Grand jury selection, 1969–1970; cuid38 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Huggins-Seale trial summaries, 1970–1971; cuid39 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Jail conditions pleadings, 1970–1971; cuid40 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Jail conditions: reading materials, 1970; cuid41 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Jail conditions and prisoner's rights, 1970–1971; cuid42 (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
  - John J. Huggins, Jr., Circa 1969; cuid43 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - John J. Huggins, Jr., Circa 1969; cuid44 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 136)
  - Jury challenge, Circa 1970-1971; cuid45 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Jury challenge, Circa 1970-1971; cuid46 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 137)
  - Jury challenge Amicus Brief, 1970; cuid47 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Jury challenge computer print-outs, Circa 1970; cuid48 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 138)
  - Jury challenge exhibits, Circa 1971; cuid49 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Jury challenge expert witness, 1968–1970; cuid50 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Jury challenge legal materials and memoranda, Circa 1970-1971; cuid51 (Box 4, Folder 48-49)
  - Jury challenge State v. David papers and other cases, 1961–1970; cuid52 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Jury challenge subpoenas and witnesses Roraback, 1970; cuid53 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Jury materials, 1970–1971; cuid54 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Kidnapping, 1969; cuid55 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Liberation News Service by John Bancroft, 1970; cuid56 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Lonnie Mclucas complaints, and motion to dismiss, 1970–1971; cuid57 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Loretta Luckes statement, 1969; cuid58 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Motion for mental exam, 1970–1973; cuid59 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Motion for production of body and coroner's inquest, 1969–1970; cuid60 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Motion to dismiss publicity, 1970–1971; cuid61 (Box 6, Folder 59-60)
  - Motion to dismiss publicity subpoenas, 1970–1971; cuid62 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Motion to suppress—Ahern transcripts, Circa 1969-1971; cuid63 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Motion to vacate security order, 1969; cuid64 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Nature and History of the Black Panther Party, Circa 1969; cuid65 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Panther cases: the tapes, 1969–1971; cuid66 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    Transcripts of tapes made during the interrogation of Alex Rackley with related notes and correspondence.
  - "The Panthers and the Police: A Pattern of Genocide?" New Yorker article by Edward Jay Epstein, 1971; cuid67 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Petition to free Ericka, 1970; cuid68 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Pleadings, 1969–1971; cuid69 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Pleadings (temporary restraining order), 1970–1971; cuid70 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Pre-trial detention conditions, 1969–1971; cuid71 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Pre-trial detention documents, 1968–1971; cuid72 (Box 7, Folder 71-72)
  - Request to charge the jury, 1971; cuid73 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Requested readings, Circa 1969-1970; cuid74 (Box 7, Folder 74-75)
  - Requested readings, cuid75 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 139)
  - Research assistants information, 1970–1971; cuid76 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Rory Hithe and Landon Williams Denver proceedings, 1969–1972; cuid77 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Search and seizure standing, Circa 1970; cuid78 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - State's Attorney—appointment and powers, 1969–1970; cuid79 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Statement on Warren Kimbro by Ericka Huggins, Circa 1969; cuid80 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Suppression hearings, FBI subpoenas and motion to quash, 1969–1971; cuid81 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Time schedule charts, Circa 1970; cuid82 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Trial exhibit: Transcript of Bobby Seale's speech delivered at Battel Chapel Yale University, 1969; cuid83 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Voir dire, 1970–1971; cuid84 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Warren Kimbro testimonial, Circa 1959-1971; cuid85 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Yale and May Day, 1970; cuid86 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    Includes letters from Yale officials including Yale President Kingman Brewster, secretary Reuben A. Holden and dean of Yale Law School Louis H. Pollak to alumni and parents on issues relating to the Black Panther trials. A memorandum to the Yale community from the trial report committee providing a summary of the of the case is also included.
- Correspondence, 1969-1972; Series II
  The series includes letters to and from Catherine Roraback and Ericka Huggins. Letters received by Ericka Huggins while she was imprisoned include one from Angela Davis. Letters to Black Panthers Landon Williams and Rory Hithe from Ericka Huggins are also included. Correspondence to and from Catherine Roraback documents interests in the trial and includes letters from lawyers such as Charles Garry, who defended Bobby Seale during the New Haven Black Panther trial.
  - Correspondence to and from Ericka Huggins
    - Davis, Angela, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Roraback, Catherine, 1969–1971 (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - Williams, Landon, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Unidentified, 1969–1971 (Box 8, Folder 90)
      Includes letter to Michael (Mikel), a friend of Ericka Huggins.
  - Correspondence to and from Catherine Roraback
    - Avery, Mike, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - "B" general, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 92)
    - Bass, Stanley, 1970–1971 (Box 8, Folder 93)
    - Bramhall, Jennifer, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - Caplan, Jerome, 1970–1972 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Capron, Barbara, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - Cerruti, Gene, Circa 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - Circuit Court of Connecticut, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - Colfax, David, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 99)
    - Dreyfus, Benjamin, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - Eaton, Wade, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - Everitt, Charles, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Fitchtenbaum, Leoand Myrna, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Foner, Moe, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Garry, Charles, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Glen, Kristin Booth, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Goldring, Jack, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Goldring, Jack, 1970 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 140)
    - Guggenheim, Martin, 1969–1970 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Hanson, Bruce, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Johnson, George A., 1969 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - "K" general, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Kinoy, Arthur, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Lach, Helen, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Moore, Vernon, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Olds, Bill, Circa 1971 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - "P" general, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Price, Hugh, 1969–1970 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Psarakis, Emanuel, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Schwartz, Helene E., 1971 (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Smith, Edwin, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Tyler, Cheever, 1971–1972 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Weinglass, Leonard I., 1971 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Wolff, Rick, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Unidentified, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 124)
- Personal Papers, 1969-1975; Series III
  The series includes the personal papers of Ericka Huggins and Catherine Roraback. Ericka Huggins papers document her time in prison. Poems and other writings written by Huggins about her imprisonment and the Black Panther Party are included. Requested reading materials include communist publications such as Selected Works of Mao Tse-Tung (1967). The series also contains documents related to the possible publishing of a book of poems by Ericka Huggins and Angela Davis. Catherine Roraback's personal papers consist of a painting entitled "Niantic" from Nancy Schulman.
  - Ericka Huggins
    - Prison writings, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Poems book negotiations, 1971–1972 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Receipts, 1969–1971 (Box 8, Folder 127)
    - Catherine Roraback
      - "Niantic" watercolor painting from Nancy Schulman, 1975 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 141)
- Restricted Fragile Material, Circa 1969–1971
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 10 contains restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 13 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 142)
  - Box 9, folder 128 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 143)
  - Box 9, folders 129 and 130 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 144)
  - Box 9, folder 131 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 145)
  - Box 2, folder 28 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 146)
  - Box 9, folder 132 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 147)
  - Box 9, folder 133 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 148)
  - Box 3, folder 37 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 149)
  - Box 9, folder 134 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 150)
  - Box 9, folder 136 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 151)
  - Box 9, folder 137 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 152)
  - Box 4, folder 45 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 153)
  - Box 4, folder 47 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 154)
  - Box 6, folder 61 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 155)
  - Box 6, folder 66 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 156)
  - Box 9, folder 139 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 157)
  - Box 7, folder 77 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 158)
  - Box 7, folder 79 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 159)
  - Box 8, folder 85 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 160)
  - Box 9, folder 140 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 161)